[Antony McMullen] Welcome, everybody, some gentle tones.
[Antony McMullen] That was the xylophone that was used for ABC radio very few years ago, when this was the ABC radio studio.
[Antony McMullen] You would have woken up to that from a certain vintage.
[Antony McMullen] So welcome, everyone, to the inaugural Basil's Table.
[Antony McMullen] I'd firstly like to start by acknowledging the righty people of the Kulin Nation, and I pay my respects to their elders past and present.
[Antony McMullen] And in particular, I'd like to mention the very many indigenous and Aboriginal cooperatives across the state, many of which go under the radar.
[Antony McMullen] And I think there's a great opportunity with the cooperative movement to make links.
[Antony McMullen] The sixth principle of cooperatives is cooperation amongst cooperatives.
[Antony McMullen] So I think that's something that we can all sort of focus on in terms of our duty to support reconciliation, restitution and all those sorts of things that we need to think about.
[Antony McMullen] My name is Antony.
[Antony McMullen] I'm the chair of the 888 Co-operative causeway Limited.
[Audience?] Who thought of that?
[Antony McMullen] No.
[Antony McMullen] The idea is 888 is a balance between work and recreation and rest.
[Antony McMullen] Co-operative is about the relationship that we have with each other.
[Antony McMullen] We're working towards the common good, which is the causeway, which is our little headquarters, which is just down the road.
[Antony McMullen] So our little cooperative has a cooperative desk space, and our cooperative is a member of this club, is a corporate member.
[Antony McMullen] So this is how we can run events right here as we have it tonight.
[Antony McMullen] But this is a bit different.
[Antony McMullen] We're trying something a bit different tonight.
[Antony McMullen] So the theme tonight is banking on the future in a climate of change.
[Antony McMullen] obviously, in australia, we've been through a very difficult time as a country in terms of the tragic bushfires.
[Antony McMullen] And it's a time where it's sometimes difficult to hold some hope or optimism or something that, you know, something creative.
[Antony McMullen] So the idea behind this series of discussions is to actually talk to people who are doing good stuff, both seasoned and emerging, and make links between people and come along.
[Antony McMullen] So that's why we started off with a bit of food and a drink and introducing ourselves to each other and building links.
[Antony McMullen] And often that's a value as well of going to an event like this.
[Antony McMullen] So in 1996, a quarter of all australians were members of what was then called a credit union.
[Antony McMullen] So you still get credit unions, you still get building societies.
[Antony McMullen] Often now they're called customer-owned banks, but they're all the same thing.
[Antony McMullen] It's where members have an ownership stake.
[Antony McMullen] Today, fast forward, I don't know what the proportion of customer-owned or member-owned financial institutions are of this figure, but eight out of 10 of us are members of a cooperative or a mutual.
[Antony McMullen] A lot of us don't know that, but I reckon most people here would.
[Antony McMullen] It's like a pretty educated world.
[Antony McMullen] So you probably know that stat already, I reckon.
[Antony McMullen] So in 1996, historian Gary Lewis, who recently passed away, had some interesting observations to make about credit unions.
[Antony McMullen] And I thought I'd kick things off before introducing our speakers with a couple of his observations.
[Antony McMullen] And I've just gotten to that age, you know, I'm in my 40s and now I'm finding, you know how you still look at people and they go like this?
[Antony McMullen] And suddenly, it's only the last year.
[Antony McMullen] So I'm just getting on top.
[Antony McMullen] A few years.
[Antony McMullen] All right.
[Antony McMullen] Since the Second World War, australian credit unions have defeated usury, pioneered innovative financial services, improved competition in and moulded the shape of the finance industry and broadened the democratization of wealth.
[Antony McMullen] They have demonstrated that ordinary people, cooperating to meet their financial needs, employing appropriate technology and expertise, can achieve quite remarkable economic outcomes.
[Antony McMullen] This study, this book, shows the ability of credit unions to apply unorthodox democratic remedies to problems that would normally cripple other businesses.
[Antony McMullen] australian credit unions first include loan protection insurance at no extra cost, free direct payroll deductions for members.
[Antony McMullen] The first ATMs were in a credit union.
[Antony McMullen] EFTPOS came out of the credit union movement in australia.
[Antony McMullen] The first international visa ATM withdrawal in the world came out of the credit union movement in 1984.
[Antony McMullen] Telephone activated home banking services.
[Antony McMullen] That's why I remember using that when I joined Endeavour Credit Union back in the day.
[Antony McMullen] You'd ring up and you'd use your touch tone and you'd be able to move money across and all that.
[Antony McMullen] It was very, very innovative.
[Antony McMullen] You probably still can do that in some quarters.
[Antony McMullen] Credit unions have been at the forefront of providing value and things like the chip card was a first for credit unions.
[Antony McMullen] The largest providers of personal loans and visa debt cards in australia when this book was written.
[Antony McMullen] That was then.
[Antony McMullen] At the moment, we've got a lot of innovation happening with start up banks.
[Antony McMullen] They're a platform.
[Antony McMullen] I heard on the radio a particular start up platform type of bank had...
[Antony McMullen] They said, Oh, yeah, we can give these great interest rates.
[Antony McMullen] And then I asked about how many people they employ.
[Antony McMullen] And, you know, it was very low.
[Antony McMullen] It's like 40 or 50 people employed by this new sort of start up bank.
[Antony McMullen] So there is innovation going out there.
[Antony McMullen] And it'd be interesting to hear from our speaker about what's happening in that area.
[Antony McMullen] But the purpose of tonight really is to go a little deeper than the day to day, to go a little bit about why people get involved in this area that we call the social economy, why people would get involved in credit unions or housing co-ops and various things like that.
[Antony McMullen] And again, in this history book, I found something that I just thought I would mention.
[Antony McMullen] Is it an acrostic when you say the words and each word has a thing?
[Antony McMullen] It's like an acrostic.
[Antony McMullen] My kids do it.
[Antony McMullen] I think that's an acrostic, isn't it?
[Audience] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[Antony McMullen] Mutual aid.
[Antony McMullen] Now, this was in 1956 by the Young Christian Workers, who are a big part of the Whole Credit Union movement.
[Antony McMullen] Money when you need it.
[Antony McMullen] Under easy repayment terms, training in thrift, United Fund of Members Savings, available for loans, low interest rates, aid to lessor financial worry, independence from exploitation, deposit interest better than bank.
[Antony McMullen] And so hopefully that's still the case.
[Antony McMullen] Mutual aid.
[Antony McMullen] Now, again, I'm struggling.
[Antony McMullen] I really need glasses.
[Antony McMullen] Okay, but I would actually like to get to the most important part, which is introducing these two people.
[Antony McMullen] So we have Basil and his table.
[Antony McMullen] And we have Rowan Dowland from Bank australia.
[Antony McMullen] So Basil, you would have read the bio in the promotional material.
[Antony McMullen] My relationship with Basil started when he taught me community development back in the day in the 90s.
[Antony McMullen] And we kept that up.
[Antony McMullen] And he's been someone that's committed himself to community development, development of community over many, many years.
[Antony McMullen] So he is bringing that experience along tonight.
[Antony McMullen] Rowan Dowland heads up strategy and planning at Bank australia.
[Antony McMullen] So I assume he's got the telescope out at times and is looking out.
[Antony McMullen] But tonight we're going to also look a little bit inwards and seeing what this social economy leader has to say about his commitment to his work.
[Antony McMullen] So without further ado, I'm going to hand the mic over and we're going to start the Basil's Table.
[Basil Varghese] I've got a microphone here.
[Basil Varghese] Well, thank you, Antony, for that introduction, and thank you all those people who have come here today, which is wonderful.
[Basil Varghese] So thank you, those people that I do know, and those that I'm going to get to know.
[Basil Varghese] I really appreciate the fact that you have come here.
[Basil Varghese] This is...
[Basil Varghese] just good to take a ride.
[Basil Varghese] Hello?
[Audience] Yeah.
[Basil Varghese] Did you hear me before?
[Basil Varghese] I will go to repeat that.
[Audience] No.
[Basil Varghese] And it's actually a great honor and privilege here to be with Rowan, whom I, we have actually had two conversations.
[Basil Varghese] And he is a very impressive man who has committed himself really to an area of life that I am not all that familiar with, because I, when it comes to money, I'm hopeless.
[Basil Varghese] As a matter of fact, friends who know me know that I'm actually just terrible when it comes to money management.
[Basil Varghese] And yet, I do know that money has been useful, as to quote someone famous, tainted as it is.
[Basil Varghese] It actually is important to get things done.
[Basil Varghese] So, I've now got more and more involved, mainly because of Antony, with the 888, and understand that we really need to get our heads around the whole aspect of profit.
[Basil Varghese] And we also have to get our heads around the importance of what is it to be not greedy.
[Basil Varghese] But I'll elaborate on that later.
[Basil Varghese] Well, I'd like to now ask Rowan, because we have this thing.
[Basil Varghese] Should you have the first question or should I have the first question?
[Basil Varghese] Now, I decided, you're my guest or our guest, you should actually be the person who actually responds to my question.
[Basil Varghese] We flip these backwards and forwards so many times.
[Basil Varghese] But hopefully, we will dial it.
[Basil Varghese] So, in terms of the question here, what is it about corporatives that attracted you to one and caused you to stay for the past 25 years or so?
[Rowan Dowland] Thanks, Basil, and thanks for the introduction as well, Antony.
[Rowan Dowland] The book that Antony referred to tonight, there's only two copies of it in australia, I understand.
[Rowan Dowland] No, Antony's got one and I've got one.
[Rowan Dowland] You've got one as well, there's three.
[Rowan Dowland] Fantastic.
[Rowan Dowland] I was given a copy of this book on the very first day that I joined our credit union, which was the SEC credit union.
[Rowan Dowland] Some of you may remember that at the time.
[Rowan Dowland] It was the largest GELD SEC, cracking how things change in Victoria.
[Rowan Dowland] I still carry my copy around and I still referred to it.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm talking to new staff who join the now a bank, customer-owned cooperative bank.
[Rowan Dowland] Absolutely by coincidence, the paragraph that you read out tonight is one of the paragraphs that I share with all new people coming to join the bank.
[Rowan Dowland] because I just think it's so critically important that as we're building banks for the future, we never forget our past and we never forget our legacy and we never forget those people, those pioneers, those people who were brave and bold, who had the courage to actually form a cooperative or credit union movement in australia.
[Rowan Dowland] If we lose sight of the values that the bravery, the sense of purpose that our founders had in australia, then I think we actually lose something from our culture and our DNA.
[Rowan Dowland] So, Basil, why did I join the cooperative movement, which is over 28 years ago?
[Rowan Dowland] I don't know a lot about money either, I've got to tell you.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm not a banker at all.
[Rowan Dowland] But there is a driving hypothesis, I guess, that I've been trying to prove throughout my life.
[Rowan Dowland] And my career started within the property industry here in Melbourne, in the real estate industry.
[Rowan Dowland] From a very young boy, I always wanted to be in the property industry, real estate industry, and I was offered the opportunity to study and do a cadetship in those days with one of the largest real estate firms here in Melbourne.
[Rowan Dowland] But within a very, very short period of time, I realized that my values were not aligned to the values of the property industry, which were all about individuals, commission driven individuals, seeking to acquire wealth without having a sense of community.
[Rowan Dowland] It was about, I win when you lose.
[Rowan Dowland] And I stayed within that industry for four years and then took an about base, 180 degree turn.
[Rowan Dowland] And went from quite a privileged career and position in the real estate industry and joined the Ministry of housing here, working with homeless people across Melbourne and working with women's refuges, working with the Gill Memorial and other institutions that were providing housing and accommodation to homeless people and worked within both the government housing sector and the community housing sector for about 10 years in total.
[Rowan Dowland] My next move was to try and find a business model that combined the commercial discipline of running a business together with the experience of the things, the aspects that I liked of the government and community sector, which was a real strong sense of social purpose and social justice and existing for the purpose of enhancing the quality of people and their lives in a strong sense of community.
[Rowan Dowland] And my mum had been a teacher and she was a member of one of the teacher based credit unions here in Melbourne.
[Rowan Dowland] And she was what was called in those days a member rep that they had.
[Rowan Dowland] And so in fact, I'd never been a customer of a bank.
[Rowan Dowland] I'd only ever been a member of a credit union.
[Rowan Dowland] So I thought I would try the experience of joining a credit union here in Melbourne and join the SEC credit union, which at the time was the largest credit union here in Victoria.
[Rowan Dowland] And my sense was that the model had enormous opportunity.
[Rowan Dowland] I think there was a period of time with credit unions where they lost their way.
[Rowan Dowland] They lost a sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] But I believe strongly in the cooperative model, both and looked internationally at the strength of the cooperative model, not just in banking, but across a broad range of industries and sectors.
[Rowan Dowland] And I believe that if we could build a strong cooperative and align with a strong sense of purpose, then we could create a sustainable business model.
[Rowan Dowland] And that's going back into the 90s.
[Rowan Dowland] And I've been in the industry now for 28 years.
[Rowan Dowland] We've built a credit union myself and my colleagues have built a credit union into australia's first cooperative bank.
[Rowan Dowland] Those that are not familiar with Bank australia, we became the first cooperative bank in australia in 2011.
[Rowan Dowland] In Europe, cooperative banks, take a country like Germany.
[Rowan Dowland] Germany's banking system is clearly very significant.
[Rowan Dowland] Banking industry, about 45% of banking in Germany is done through cooperative banks.
[Rowan Dowland] And it kind of always intrigued me that you can have such strong cooperative banks in other parts of the world, particularly Europe, but less so here.
[Rowan Dowland] And one of the ambitions that we did have was to establish australia's first cooperative bank, which we did in 2011.
[Rowan Dowland] In 2015, we renamed that bank, Bank australia.
[Rowan Dowland] And ever since doing that, we've been growing the business very, very strong and very successfully.
[Rowan Dowland] But it hasn't always been enough challenges and enough opportunities over that period of time to keep me engaged in the business.
[Rowan Dowland] And we had lost our way in the late 90s.
[Rowan Dowland] In fact, let me just tell you the story very briefly.
[Rowan Dowland] At that time, I believe it was essential to build scale within credit unions.
[Rowan Dowland] So when I started, it was a 50 million, we managed $50 million in assets.
[Rowan Dowland] Today, we manage around $7 billion in assets.
[Rowan Dowland] And we would still be describing ourselves as sub-scale.
[Rowan Dowland] So as part of the way of being able to build scale in the 90s, we acquired a number of credit unions, smaller credit unions.
[Rowan Dowland] We brought them into the group.
[Rowan Dowland] So whilst I started in the SEC credit union, I also worked in the ANSET credit union and the David Syme credit union.
[Rowan Dowland] We acquired the CSIRO staff credit union and a number of other credit unions.
[Rowan Dowland] And in fact, today, there's some 72 credit unions that form the Bank australia group.
[Rowan Dowland] But what we discovered in late 90s was that without a strong sense of purpose, then you can lose your way very quickly and you can become quite irrelevant to the customers that own either the credit union or the bank.
[Rowan Dowland] And I remember listening in on a conversation down in the Latrobe Valley.
[Rowan Dowland] We have a business in the Latrobe Valley based off the SEC days.
[Rowan Dowland] And I remember listening to callers coming into the call center and they were saying things like, you guys have just got bigger, but you've not got better.
[Rowan Dowland] I don't understand why you exist any longer.
[Rowan Dowland] I understood the purpose behind the credit union as a scientist with the CSIRO or a pilot with ANTCEP or someone, an editor at David Syme.
[Rowan Dowland] You represented a banking opportunity or banking option for people that could associate, could identify with a defined group, a defined community, and you are no longer the staff credit unit, the pilots or empower workers.
[Rowan Dowland] I don't understand it anymore.
[Rowan Dowland] I sat down with the CEO at the time and said, I think we're actually in strife here.
[Rowan Dowland] We've been building this business and today, and at that point in time, we're probably 650 million dollars in assets.
[Rowan Dowland] We were growing, we were existing as opposed to having a strong sense of understanding why we existed and the purpose behind why we existed.
[Rowan Dowland] John at the time said, look, you're right.
[Rowan Dowland] This is not a way to build this business if we can't define, articulate our strong sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] You go and spend a few months spending time with cooperatives around the world, to try and understand what it is that makes those businesses successful.
[Rowan Dowland] I came back in australia after a number of months and said, I think I've discovered it.
[Rowan Dowland] Now, what we've been doing as we've been building this business, we lost sight of a strong sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] People could no longer identify with the business and we've defined the business according historically according to jobs or geography.
[Rowan Dowland] That's how the credit unions were.
[Rowan Dowland] They were the industry based credit unions, they were parish based credit unions or they were community based credit unions defined by geography.
[Rowan Dowland] I said the future is no longer jobs or geography or vocation or location.
[Rowan Dowland] The future of cooperatives in banking and our cooperative was attitudes and values.
[Rowan Dowland] It's what people believe.
[Rowan Dowland] If people believe in a strong sense of community, if people believe that we as a business can help and power them to use their monies in ways that create strong social, environmental, cultural and economic impact.
[Rowan Dowland] If we can use money in a way that enhances their lives, enhances the lives of others, and improves the quality of life that we exist in terms of the planet and the environment, then I think we've defined a new space in the australian banking sector.
[Rowan Dowland] That's what we did in 2002.
[Rowan Dowland] We put a merger together that gives a bit more scale, but on the basis of saying, we're going to be a business that now defines its purpose, not according to jobs and geography, but according to the old traditional credit union values.
[Rowan Dowland] You bring a community of interests together, and through that community of interests, now defined by our attitudes and values, not jobs and geography, we're going to get those people to save together, and we're going to invest those monies in ways that improve the quality of their lives, the lives of others and the planet.
[Rowan Dowland] We're going to use that money in ways that make a positive impact in the community, in the world, around the issues that are important to them.
[Rowan Dowland] What I really love about that is that it is completely consistent with the principles, the philosophies, the values that underpin cooperatives, banks that were formed in Germany in the mid 1800s.
[Rowan Dowland] So they brought together groups of artisans and farmers who were unbanked, said, let's save together and let's provide an opportunity for these communities to bank.
[Rowan Dowland] And we're doing exactly the same today.
[Rowan Dowland] The issues change for our customers, and that's the exciting part.
[Rowan Dowland] That's the thing that keeps us quite dynamic.
[Rowan Dowland] We say these days that we need to be a good bank because you can't trade off values.
[Rowan Dowland] You need to be a good bank and a force for good.
[Rowan Dowland] You need to be able to compete with banking product and services and technology and all the things that Anthony referred to, Visa cards and the like.
[Rowan Dowland] But none of that's going to differentiate us in the marketplace.
[Rowan Dowland] It's being a force for good that differentiates us in the marketplace.
[Rowan Dowland] So we know from our customers the things that are important to them.
[Rowan Dowland] We know that the number one issue that's important to our customers at the moment is climate change, the future of the planet.
[Rowan Dowland] And we know that if we can align their money, invest their money in ways that create positive environmental impact, then we're meeting our purpose, we're meeting our needs as a cooperative.
[Rowan Dowland] And at any one time we know the 10 or 11 most important issues that are important to our customers, climate change, renewable energy, fair treatment of refugees, closing the gap on indigenous mental health issues, homelessness, house affordability.
[Rowan Dowland] We know what those issues are.
[Rowan Dowland] And we continue to align the business of banking to those issues and invest our customers' money in ways that have positive impacts in those areas.
[Rowan Dowland] And I've been doing it for 28 years.
[Rowan Dowland] I can share with you that last month, so the business is now 62 years old, as I said, manages about $7 billion in assets.
[Rowan Dowland] Last year, we attracted more people into the bank than any other month in the past 62 years.
[Rowan Dowland] Purely on the basis of the principles that underpinned the cooperative when we formed it in 1957 and the same principles that underpinned cooperatives when they were formed in the 1850s.
[Rowan Dowland] Providing a values-based or values-led approach to banking.
[Rowan Dowland] The vast majority of people who joined us last month, record number, almost 4,000 people joined us, switched out of the four major banks to join Bank australia last month, joined us because they wanted to empower themselves in a way that helped make a positive difference on climate change.
[Rowan Dowland] It was the fires that occurred throughout the summer period where people said, I need to do something here.
[Rowan Dowland] We can see that, we can track that throughout the year.
[Rowan Dowland] We know there's a campaign about to be launched around animal exports.
[Rowan Dowland] We have a strong position on animal exports.
[Rowan Dowland] You may have seen some of our advertising.
[Rowan Dowland] The things we do, do the things we don't do.
[Rowan Dowland] And as the community becomes aware and more aware that they can empower themselves in ways that bring about positive changes, simply through the way they invest their money, they bank their everyday banking, we've seen influx of business coming into the Bank australia based purely on a strong sense of purpose, based purely on a strong sense of cooperative values.
[Rowan Dowland] And that's what keeps me here now after 28, almost 30 years, and I'm kind of getting towards the end of my career and bringing on the next generation of people to take the business forward.
[Rowan Dowland] But what I'm hoping that they learn either from myself and my experience or reading the book is that the principles of being a cooperative still stand true today.
[Rowan Dowland] They've stood the test of time.
[Rowan Dowland] They are as relevant today as they were in the 1850s, as they were in 1957 when we were born.
[Rowan Dowland] And they can still capture the imagination of people.
[Rowan Dowland] And to get 4,000 people, when I look at the 4,000 people who joined us in January, the average age was 34.
[Basil Varghese?] What?
[Basil Varghese?] That's amazing.
[Rowan Dowland] None of them, well, none, I won't say none.
[Rowan Dowland] Something in the order of about 87% of them did not factor price into their decision to switch out of one of the full major banks to Bank australia.
[Rowan Dowland] Whilst we would never trade away price, price is critically important of being cooperative.
[Rowan Dowland] They joined us because of principles and values and a strong sense of I want to, I want my money to have a positive impact in the world.
[Rowan Dowland] Now people used to say to me banks can only compete on price.
[Rowan Dowland] And I said we would never trade price away.
[Rowan Dowland] But banks can compete on purpose and you can define a space for a cooperative bank in the marketplace simply by meeting people's expectations around doing good in the world as opposed to doing harm in the world.
[Rowan Dowland] That's a really long answer to your question.
[Rowan Dowland] But I've been at it for 28 years.
[Rowan Dowland] And I kind of, as committed to it today, now the only reason why I'll step out of the business is because I've kind of hit retirement.
[Rowan Dowland] It's not because I'm any less committed to the purpose of the bank today than I was 28 years ago.
[Rowan Dowland] And when you see 4,000 people join the bank in January, and this month it's probably over, it'll be over 3,000.
[Rowan Dowland] And again, the average age is going to be somewhere around about 34, 35.
[Rowan Dowland] And they're empowering themselves to bring about positive change in the world.
[Rowan Dowland] That's incredibly cool.
[Rowan Dowland] For somebody who kind of, you know, all those years ago wanted to test the hypothesis of can a business exist for a purpose beyond profit maximization, I think we're about to give ourselves a tick.
[Rowan Dowland] Thank you.
[Rowan Dowland] The other amazing part about that is that our brand has only been in the market place really since 2017.
[Rowan Dowland] So it's a very new brand.
[Rowan Dowland] Whilst the business has been operated under all these different names for some years, it's really only been known from Bank australia since 2017.
[Rowan Dowland] And in the last week, we appeared as number 42 in australia's most trusted brands, which gives me…
[Unidentified] The meaning of life, really.
[Rowan Dowland] I just think, no, banks have lost people's trust.
[Rowan Dowland] That's why we had a Royal Commission.
[Rowan Dowland] So, within three years to be in the top number 42 and top 50 most trusted brands in australia, that gives me great hope that the people who will take over from me, who will be younger and smarter and more, they have got an amazing future to take that business up for three years from being the 42nd most trusted brand in the country to number one, all based on values.
[Rowan Dowland] That's for people who understand the value of co-operatives and understand the value of co-operative values.
[Rowan Dowland] I think that just is something, and many of us have been beating the drum for that for many years.
[Rowan Dowland] Their future is incredible.
[Basil Varghese] Well, it's interesting that none of the credit unions or the banks had to appear for the Royal Commission, while all the others had to.
[Rowan Dowland] Not a single co-operative or mutual bank appeared before the Royal Commission.
[Rowan Dowland] We all wrote submissions, but we didn't appear before.
[Rowan Dowland] The Royal Commission was not called because of the business practices of the co-operative or mutual banks in the country.
[Rowan Dowland] We know why it was called.
[Rowan Dowland] We sit, it's interesting, as a very small bank, we sit at the table of the australian Bankers Association.
[Rowan Dowland] Some people say, why would you do that?
[Rowan Dowland] Why would you sit in the same room as all the other investor owned banks in the country?
[Rowan Dowland] We're part of a global alliance for banking on values.
[Rowan Dowland] And part of our commitment as being a member of the global alliance is that we try and influence banking, try to influence the banking sector.
[Rowan Dowland] So we believe we have a responsibility to sit at the table.
[Rowan Dowland] It's kind of interesting.
[Rowan Dowland] We're the tiniest member of the ABA.
[Rowan Dowland] You're sitting at the table and there's the CEOs and deputy CEOs of all the largest banks in the country.
[Rowan Dowland] It's a bit like when I was a kid, the naughty boys used to sit on the car table at the end of the dining table.
[Rowan Dowland] Well, we're kind of the odd one out.
[Rowan Dowland] We always sit at the end of the table.
[Rowan Dowland] We're the big guys at one end and we're at the other end.
[Rowan Dowland] So we understand we were very close to the decisions around why Royal Commission was called.
[Rowan Dowland] And we understood what the practices were.
[Rowan Dowland] And we take great pride in the fact that there was no mutual cooperative bank that was part of the Royal Commission.
[Rowan Dowland] Why was the Royal Commission called?
[Rowan Dowland] The Royal Commission was called for one simple reason, in our sense.
[Rowan Dowland] It's because banks forgot why they existed in the first place.
[Rowan Dowland] They lost their sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] I just talked about, I think we're very clear on our sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] We exist for the purpose of creating mutual prosperity in the form of positive social, environmental, cultural, and economic outcomes.
[Rowan Dowland] That's what we do.
[Rowan Dowland] The four major banks, or the investor owned banks, existed for the purpose of profit maximization and incentivizing executives to earn very large remuneration at the expense of their customer and their communities.
[Rowan Dowland] That's why there was a Royal Commission.
[Rowan Dowland] They forgot the sense of purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] And we could kind of see it as a member of the ABA.
[Rowan Dowland] We could see that there was a stark difference between our purpose and the purpose of the four major banks.
[Rowan Dowland] And it's a great thing that the Royal Commission was called.
[Rowan Dowland] Really great thing.
[Rowan Dowland] I think that the...
[Rowan Dowland] I have to give credit to the banks that were either part of the process or as in terms of more than being called to present or at least invest under.
[Rowan Dowland] But I think the penny has dropped with these guys.
[Rowan Dowland] And people say, I don't get sitting around and then be on change.
[Rowan Dowland] I actually think that it will.
[Rowan Dowland] From what I see, I think the Royal Commission and other businesses like us that can demonstrate that you can be a successful business by being a purpose-led and values-based business.
[Rowan Dowland] We will influence the way other businesses operate.
[Rowan Dowland] And those guys have learned the lesson.
[Rowan Dowland] Those guys have learned the lesson that whilst they have to be profitable as we do, there has to be a way so they cannot trade off their social license for why they exist.
[Rowan Dowland] And proof will be in the pudding and time to tell and everything else.
[Rowan Dowland] But I sense that there is a much stronger realization and now amongst the investor-owned banks in the country than there's ever been before.
[Rowan Dowland] Which does, I guess, create a challenge for us too.
[Rowan Dowland] One of the things that we say in Bank australia is that we have a responsibility to continually raise the bar for responsible banking.
[Rowan Dowland] And if the Royal Commission has any positive impact, it will change the behaviors that occur within investor-owned banks in the country, which means that we need to raise the bar higher in order to be able to demonstrate that there are other things that banks can do.
[Rowan Dowland] There are other responsibilities and roles and purposes the banks can deliver.
[Rowan Dowland] That's our role.
[Rowan Dowland] But I do take some pride, I think, as everybody in the mutual banking sector should, that we weren't part of that process.
[Rowan Dowland] It wasn't called because of anything we were doing wrong.
[Basil Varghese?] Right.
[Rowan Dowland] When we, Basil and I kind of caught up for coffee a couple of times, I got to understand Basil and what makes Basil tick and his background.
[Rowan Dowland] I thought I would ask him a couple of questions too.
[Rowan Dowland] So, the first one that I wanted to ask you, Basil, was around the pursuit of profit without purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] So I kind of talked about we have a purpose, what's a profitable profit maximization is not our purpose.
[Rowan Dowland] So I want to ask Basil, the pursuit of profit without purpose assumes a couple of things.
[Rowan Dowland] It assumes that the point of life is to maximize financial wealth, that we as individuals live in an adversarial world and that this situation is inevitable.
[Rowan Dowland] And I wanted to put to Basil, we see these ideas as modern day truths, many of us, perhaps not us, but others do.
[Rowan Dowland] More so, ours, others default position.
[Rowan Dowland] So is it right that profit maximization is a default position?
[Rowan Dowland] And is that okay?
[Basil Varghese] Well, I don't think it is okay.
[Basil Varghese] That's from where I'm coming from.
[Basil Varghese] And I think that the pursuit of wealth for the sake of wealth in my book is obscene.
[Basil Varghese] because you just basically, and I know people who do that.
[Basil Varghese] So it's another thing saying I need a legitimate income to live on, but to pursue wealth for the sake of wealth and seek, totally identify with that and all that matters is to me, a most dehumanized human being.
[Basil Varghese] They might sound very good in terms of saying whether they drive what sort of car or have a mansion, blah, blah, blah, or throw a party for $21 million.
[Basil Varghese] I personally have never been impressed by that.
[Basil Varghese] I just thought it was so pathetic when I see so many people who are struggling just to live, to live like in Melbourne.
[Basil Varghese] I mean, I'm always left with an existential issue when I see a homeless person.
[Basil Varghese] Often, I'm left with a sense by saying, here I am in this country, supposed to be wealthy, and here we have homeless people.
[Basil Varghese] Yet I also know there are people who are concerned about it, but I've been involved with that and it's like knocking your head on a brick wall, because you find that really a lot of the development are actually in the hands of the developers and they're into social housing, which I'm not against.
[Basil Varghese] But if you bring up the notion of homelessness, they run a mile.
[Basil Varghese] They just don't want to hear you.
[Basil Varghese] It sort of reminds me going back in the 60s, this is it, tells you how old I am.
[Basil Varghese] It goes back to the 60s, is I can remember when we talked about indigenous issues, very few people actually even considered it.
[Basil Varghese] At least now you have a discourse in society.
[Basil Varghese] So there are ghosts.
[Basil Varghese] I like to sort of think that the sense of there's something, I am diminished when I know another human being is diminished.
[Basil Varghese] The existential issue for me is, am I a part of this as well?
[Basil Varghese] because I have a reasonable accommodation.
[Basil Varghese] I think I've shared this with friends of mine, like even when I went to Kenya, or even to Moleste, you go to a hotel, you stay in a hotel, and it's wonderful.
[Basil Varghese] I enjoy the accommodation, I enjoy the food, I enjoy the company, I enjoy the conversation, I enjoy the wine, I enjoy the food.
[Basil Varghese] And yet, when I went to bed, I was aware of the fact that there were hundreds of people who did not even have a bed.
[Basil Varghese] Now, what does that mean?
[Basil Varghese] Does that mean I have to be out there in the streets without a bed?
[Basil Varghese] No, I couldn't do that.
[Basil Varghese] Although I had a friend of mine who did precisely that and he died with them.
[Basil Varghese] I don't think I am that virtuous or call to such courage.
[Basil Varghese] I just don't have that.
[Basil Varghese] But I think it is incumbent on us to think about, take something like homelessness.
[Basil Varghese] I think we have some very good models.
[Basil Varghese] I mean, I talk about the Finnish model.
[Basil Varghese] They have actually sorted it out.
[Basil Varghese] Whenever I talk to groups concerned with homelessness, they say about things like, oh, it's all the drug addiction.
[Basil Varghese] True.
[Basil Varghese] It's all the sort of abuse they've had.
[Basil Varghese] You can have all this therapeutic intervention.
[Basil Varghese] But I say, for goodness sake, have a roof over their head first.
[Basil Varghese] Then you can bring in all the notion of how to make them feel comfortable or wanted or loved, whatever term you want to use.
[Basil Varghese] Now, the reason I suppose I think social banking, I don't know whether you're taking homelessness on.
[Rowan Dowland?] We go.
[Basil Varghese] There you are.
[Basil Varghese] He does.
[Basil Varghese] So that's good news.
[Basil Varghese] Now, what I also wanted to share is that I think you mentioned about culture.
[Basil Varghese] We must have mentioned about culture.
[Basil Varghese] I think what's happened to us is that there's always been a tension between my individualism and how I relate to others.
[Basil Varghese] I think that's been a perennial story, at least in the West.
[Basil Varghese] And I suspect also in the East, but we sort of culturally do it differently.
[Basil Varghese] And I think what's happened now is that apart from that, we also become more and more commodified in the way we engage in the world.
[Basil Varghese] That even good acts are seen in monetary terms.
[Basil Varghese] So we have even lost a sense, like altruism, it's sort of airbrushed.
[Basil Varghese] It's like it doesn't exist.
[Basil Varghese] And you can have some very good sophisticated arguments to say it doesn't exist.
[Basil Varghese] And so I'm not suggesting in any ways that I have the solutions, but I would like to think we should look at how we actually become human in this process of being connected.
[Basil Varghese] I know from experience that whenever I experience a disconnect, I experience a pain.
[Basil Varghese] And whenever I experience a connectedness, I experience a joy.
[Basil Varghese] Now, we can talk about that very much in terms of individuals and individual attributions.
[Basil Varghese] So for example, years and years I used to talk about poverty.
[Basil Varghese] And, you know, you could go back to absolute poverty, relative poverty, and poverty to quote Gandhi is a form of violence.
[Basil Varghese] But the real poverty is also to do with the poverty of the imagination, the poverty of living, the poverty of having a passion, the poverty of not being able to be sensitive to a poem, or not being able to enjoy a piece of theatre, or not being able to enjoy the magnificence of literature, or not being able to see the importance of art.
[Basil Varghese] And I think to do that, that's where I'd like to think good banking comes.
[Basil Varghese] It's actually got to have a certain level of material sustenance to be able to enjoy this.
[Basil Varghese] And I think life is meant to be enjoyed.
[Basil Varghese] I don't subscribe to the theory that, you know, you've got to somehow have a painful existence.
[Basil Varghese] It doesn't mean that we don't experience pain.
[Basil Varghese] All of us in life, as we journey through life, experience a pain.
[Basil Varghese] And it could be a pain on a number of levels.
[Basil Varghese] Now, as Antony said, we'd like to go deeper into this.
[Basil Varghese] So, I'd like your sort of reflections on, I think you're doing a great service, incidentally.
[Basil Varghese] So, I'm not in any way trying to diminish it.
[Basil Varghese] But I'd like us to sort of think about, how do we go now from a local, just on that basis, I think the great thing about in the past, what I've known about, say, the 1800s of other corporates, it is geographically based.
[Basil Varghese] So, you had a community that was actually that knew each other.
[Basil Varghese] And then you had a community that actually cared for one another.
[Basil Varghese] We don't have that anymore, entirely, except for certain groups.
[Basil Varghese] Like, when I go and see my cousins in India, they have it.
[Basil Varghese] Or, all my uncles have passed away.
[Basil Varghese] They used to sort of just live next door.
[Basil Varghese] And then they used to talk, play cards, and then go home and talk about the village gossip.
[Basil Varghese] There was a sense of being connected.
[Basil Varghese] And I think one of the issues now in our life at the moment, and it's not surprising, I mean, the UK has got a ministry for loneliness.
[Basil Varghese] And I think that is one of the big aspects of our existence at the moment, although there are lots of people who are lonely.
[Basil Varghese] And then they try to fill in that loneliness with nonsense.
[Basil Varghese] You know, it's like, it's also been globalized in a way.
[Rowan Dowland] So, can I give you some hope?
[Rowan Dowland] Can I give you some hope and some optimism?
[Basil Varghese] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[Rowan Dowland?] One of the two words that you used in your opening address, was your hope and optimism.
[Basil Varghese] But I think I suppose the older I become, I am optimistic because I meet a lot of young people who remind me of my youth.
[Basil Varghese] And they remind me of the passion I had when I was in my 20s.
[Basil Varghese] Yes.
[Basil Varghese] Now, but there is the other aspect too, is that they are a different world.
[Basil Varghese] I mean, they are savvy.
[Basil Varghese] I mean, I am technologically challenged, for example.
[Basil Varghese] That's the word I think you used now, technologically challenged.
[Basil Varghese] And I am technologically challenged.
[Basil Varghese] And I decided that I want to do something about this, but my attempts have been rather pathetic.
[Basil Varghese] But anyway, but it's a question of actually a role.
[Basil Varghese] I'd like to think there's a role for elders.
[Basil Varghese] That's one thing the indigenous community has.
[Basil Varghese] And I think we need circles of elders who affirm young people to get on with it, whatever it is, and we should be encouraging them.
[Basil Varghese] I mean, that's just one thing that I'm in a way doing with a lot of young men that I meet, because they're terrific.
[Basil Varghese] They're trying to be, they're trying to be a good husband or a lover or a friend.
[Basil Varghese] And at the same time, they want to not come across as being chauvinistic, and they don't want to be machismo, and it's complex, because at another level, they can't express their testosterone, because they're too scared, because the women will sort of accuse them of being horrible men.
[Basil Varghese] So, they hold that back.
[Basil Varghese] They hold that back.
[Basil Varghese] So, there's this sort of stylized type of politically correct living that irritates me.
[Basil Varghese] And all they latch onto, which is like, oh, how many glasses of wine did you have?
[Basil Varghese] Or how many cigarettes do you smoke?
[Basil Varghese] Or these are sort of individual things, which are not, say, I'm against smoking, or against...
[Basil Varghese] What I'm saying is, it's easy to latch onto things like that for people to feel virtuous.
[Basil Varghese] And I'd like to think that their virtue has to go at what I would call a systemic and structural level.
[Basil Varghese] And that's where we need good policy and we could implement as a policy.
[Basil Varghese] I don't want good policy because I've read policy papers gathering dust.
[Basil Varghese] What we need is people who can implement it.
[Rowan Dowland?] And I've got a lot of hope and optimism.
[Rowan Dowland?] I think that's possible.
[Rowan Dowland?] And I think I'm a troubled egg when it comes to technology as well.
[Basil Varghese?] Oh, good.
[Basil Varghese?] Okay.
[Rowan Dowland] But I have great hope that technology is part of that.
[Rowan Dowland] If I look at the community that's now being formed as the...
[Rowan Dowland] I've used the term community, but I'm actually going to...
[Rowan Dowland] I'm trying to shift that term at the moment to movement.
[Rowan Dowland] And we were formed as Creative Unions.
[Rowan Dowland] We were described as so.
[Rowan Dowland] When I came into the industry, we were doing a movement.
[Rowan Dowland] And a movement then became an industry.
[Rowan Dowland] And I kind of want to take it back to being a movement, a movement for positive change.
[Rowan Dowland] The opportunity to actually create a movement is there through technology.
[Rowan Dowland] And I see that every day in social media.
[Rowan Dowland] I get this report on my desk every morning, which is the conversation that's occurring within social media around Bank australia and the positive things that people can do in the world with them in australia with their money.
[Rowan Dowland] And there is a conversation that's occurring right now.
[Rowan Dowland] If somebody is savvy enough to jump into Facebook or to Instagram or to Twitter, you'll probably see a conversation occurring somewhere in australia now around the role of money in society and the opportunity to create good in the world.
[Rowan Dowland] So I'm actually very optimistic and have great hope that we can just rebalance the way that we see society and that we see the role of money by using technology to go back again to principles of movement creation.
[Rowan Dowland] Go back to January, 4,000 people joined a bank because they wanted to create positive good in the world.
[Rowan Dowland] So I'm very hopeful.
[Rowan Dowland] It's then aligning that ambition that those people have for a better future through the way their money is invested to the issues that are important to them.
[Rowan Dowland] And you touched on housing, and I think you touched on it, Antony, also on innovation in your opening comments.
[Rowan Dowland] I'll give you an example of that.
[Rowan Dowland] housing is critically important.
[Rowan Dowland] I've always worked in the business of housing.
[Rowan Dowland] I've built it, sold it, developed it, managed it, financed it.
[Rowan Dowland] So housing has been core to my...
[Rowan Dowland] I fundamentally believe that security of tenure provides better quality outcomes.
[Rowan Dowland] It doesn't have to be...
[Rowan Dowland] don't have to own it, you can lease it.
[Rowan Dowland] But as long as you've got security of tenure, the evidence now, I believe, demonstrates that you have better social outcomes, economic outcomes, health outcomes, education outcomes.
[Rowan Dowland] Security of tenure delivers quality of living.
[Rowan Dowland] We, and the opportunity that we have through the Co-operative model is to test some new models.
[Rowan Dowland] Let me tell you about some models that the Co-operative model enables you to attest, because we're not chasing profit maximization, we're not chasing shareholder return, we're trying to build value, wealth in different ways.
[Rowan Dowland] Today, I had a most amazing conversation with my Impact Finance Manager around opportunities to invest in housing, house ownership for indigenous australians in partnership with the indigenous business Association of business australia, indigenous business australia Government Department.
[Rowan Dowland] One of the things that research now shows is you can rebuild trust.
[Rowan Dowland] trust has been lost in a range of different institutions, you will know that, whether it's in churches, whether it's in government and the like.
[Rowan Dowland] But you can actually help rebuild trust by way of partnership, and partnership comes naturally to cooperatives.
[Rowan Dowland] Partnerships between government and business to respond to, find solutions to social, economic, cultural issues.
[Rowan Dowland] So we're working now with indigenous business australia to find ways where we can provide housing to indigenous australians.
[Rowan Dowland] We can finance that housing, and the IVA and the government can actually carry some of the credit risk on that.
[Rowan Dowland] So all of a sudden we can provide unbankable indigenous australians the opportunity to buy housing in australia, because we approach the issue differently to the way the four major banks or an investor-owned bank, they look at the profit maximisation.
[Rowan Dowland] We look at wealth through a different lens.
[Rowan Dowland] Another example, we entered the community housing market here in Melbourne about a decade, about 12 years ago.
[Rowan Dowland] No bank in the country would touch it.
[Rowan Dowland] But the Rudd government started to provide opportunities for community housing organisations, associations to take debt on.
[Rowan Dowland] They weren't ready to take debt on.
[Rowan Dowland] Their boards weren't ready.
[Rowan Dowland] Their management weren't ready.
[Rowan Dowland] We invested probably two years of time and effort in building the capability of boards and executive teams to understand how to take debt on so that it would become less of a credit risk to us.
[Rowan Dowland] Again, the four major banks wouldn't do that because they were looking at quick profit maximisation.
[Rowan Dowland] But the corporate model said there's a better long-term dividend that can be generated here for people and our own customers if we invest the time and effort.
[Rowan Dowland] We did that to the point where we generated about $400 million worth of community housing investments across australia.
[Rowan Dowland] It got to the point where the government, and this is okay, the government then introduced and or established an organisation called NIFIC, which enabled them to use the government guarantee to bring money in, to lend money to the community housing sector at a much lower price using their AAA credit rating versus our BBB plus credit rating.
[Rowan Dowland] But guess what?
[Rowan Dowland] It probably wouldn't have happened if the cooperative hadn't been there in the first building capacity, building capability, getting these guys to a point where they could take debt on the start to build scale.
[Rowan Dowland] And it got way beyond the point.
[Rowan Dowland] We've had a lot of that money refinanced out of that sector and the government's picked that up through through NIFIC.
[Rowan Dowland] But now we've moved on to indigenous housing and then we'll move on to the next thing.
[Rowan Dowland] And we will create markets and new opportunities because that's what a cooperative model can do.
[Rowan Dowland] Cooperatives go into markets that don't work.
[Rowan Dowland] They're broken markets and go, how can you fix this?
[Rowan Dowland] How can you use the cooperative model, the cooperative principle, not based on profit maximization, but investing people's moneys in ways that create positive social environment?
[Rowan Dowland] How can you find a business model to do that?
[Rowan Dowland] We've just had a partnership with the Clean Energy Finance Corporation.
[Rowan Dowland] Together with the Clean Energy Finance Corporation, we now provide the lowest cost home loan in australia, bar none.
[Rowan Dowland] But the house has got to be sustainably designed.
[Rowan Dowland] It's got to be one star beyond the statutory limit, which encourages people to build more sustainable design housing.
[Rowan Dowland] We were the only financier that could sit down and have the discussion with NIFIC, because our purpose is different.
[Rowan Dowland] Now, it will come to a point where that model is proven, and it will become of a scale that we can't do, and the four major banks will want to come in and start financing that business.
[Rowan Dowland] Absolutely perfectly fine, because we seeded the market.
[Rowan Dowland] And then we'll move on to the next thing.
[Rowan Dowland] So, I've got great hope after all those years that we can redefine wealth, we can use innovation, and we can be hopeful and optimistic that in 2020 the Co-operative Model can still help find ways to create better quality outcomes, social, environmental, cultural, economic outcomes for people.
[Rowan Dowland] Really, really hopeful.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm a bit sad that I'm about to hit 60 and I'm going to go and retire, because there's so much time and so much opportunity in front of us that can still do good.
[Basil Varghese] Yeah, but don't retire.
[Basil Varghese] There's lots of things to do.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm going to go to Italy, as you know, and live in a community which is a very strong community in the village where I have a home, which is really built on a cooperative economy.
[Antony McMullen] I think Antony is here.
[Antony McMullen] I hate to break into this conversation, but I would like to give anyone here present an opportunity to ask a question.
[Antony McMullen] because this is a dialogue, you can ask a question to Basil or you can ask a question to Rowan.
[Antony McMullen] Now, Sonia actually has a rosing mic here and we have our first hand up there.
[Antony McMullen] So, we'll probably take two or three questions and then take a little bit from there.
[Audience] Hi Rowan, I'm changing banks tomorrow.
[Audience] I feel like a lot of us aren't very good at teaching our kids financial literacy and schools are very good at either.
[Audience] Even people who like know what they're doing in their own lives don't do a very good job.
[Audience] They don't even do anything about teaching their kids financial literacy.
[Audience] So, is there an opportunity to have a bank for kids or some kind of separate program that really targets kids and encourages them to save and inspires them to be financially independent?
[Rowan Dowland] That's a very hard.
[Rowan Dowland] A bank for kids.
[Basil Varghese?] Well, a friend of mine wanted to do that, but she didn't end up being out to do it because she got sick.
[Rowan Dowland] Really?
[Rowan Dowland] You know, it's been a frustration.
[Rowan Dowland] I think the Co-operative Movement, the Mutual Banking Movement in australia has done some really, really cool things.
[Rowan Dowland] But it's missed some amazing opportunities along the way too.
[Rowan Dowland] You know, the fact that the Dolomites Commonwealth Bank got in, and it was very clever.
[Rowan Dowland] And you probably saw that it's been accused of grooming kids in a nice possible way.
[Rowan Dowland] But they were very clever and very shrewd the way they did it.
[Rowan Dowland] They paid the schools.
[Rowan Dowland] Schools are always looking for money.
[Rowan Dowland] So the Commonwealth Bank paid the schools for every account that they opened.
[Rowan Dowland] And as a consequence of that, many of you probably had Dolomite accounts.
[Rowan Dowland] And it's amazing.
[Rowan Dowland] Everybody had a Dolomite.
[Rowan Dowland] The penetration was amazing.
[Rowan Dowland] So I hope that we've got to burn that, right?
[Rowan Dowland] I hope that through the hope and the optimism and the things that we're talking about, re-educating people about the role of money in society.
[Rowan Dowland] I mean, I've sent in so many of focus groups over the years where you talk to people about, here's the question that we often ask people in australia.
[Rowan Dowland] What does a bank do with your money?
[Rowan Dowland] And I've had people say they put it in a safe.
[Rowan Dowland] And then you ask, or the researcher says, and then, so when you go in and do a withdrawal, what do you think happens?
[Rowan Dowland] And they say, well, they take it out of the safe.
[Rowan Dowland] But the level of financial literacy in this country is beyond belief, is so low.
[Rowan Dowland] People do not understand what banks do with their money.
[Rowan Dowland] And part of our campaigning at the moment is to demonstrate that banks do some good things and they do some bad things.
[Rowan Dowland] So if you don't want your money financing fossil fuels in the country, don't bank with the full major banks.
[Rowan Dowland] If you don't want your money financing live export trade in australia, or tobacco or gambling or weapons and things, don't bank with the full major banks.
[Rowan Dowland] So I'm hoping that we're trying to seed a process of educating australians around the role of money.
[Rowan Dowland] My strategy to do that, my long-term plan is actually not to start with the kids.
[Rowan Dowland] It's to try to get the adults, the parents to understand that the power of money and get them to educate their kids.
[Rowan Dowland] Now we went out to our customers at the beginning of the year and said to them, we do this every year, who'd like to be the face of Bank australia in 2020?
[Rowan Dowland] You can imagine any other bank asking that question.
[Rowan Dowland] Like nobody would ever respond.
[Rowan Dowland] Who'd want to be the face of NAB or Combank?
[Rowan Dowland] Like you'd get nothing back.
[Rowan Dowland] So we put that out and we've got to shut it down within 12 hours because we just get overwhelmed.
[Rowan Dowland] So within 12 hours we're 160 people.
[Rowan Dowland] Not only say they want to be the face of Bank australia, but they gave us their story and the amazing things that they're doing in their life and the pictures and the whole thing.
[Rowan Dowland] About number three that came in was a five year old who said, I put my pocket money with Bank australia because I want to save the animals.
[Rowan Dowland] So he becomes one of the faces of Bank australia and we will tell those stories out across the country.
[Rowan Dowland] And I'm hoping that my five year old is telling the stories around the role of money is as powerful as an adult telling the story about the role of money and getting to the younger kids.
[Rowan Dowland] But our average age, one of the things that we were running a risk of in terms of the business back in the early 90s when we said we could have changed, we could have do some stuff, we were going to fall off a cliff around age and customer base.
[Rowan Dowland] And if we had not made a change, we would have, we would have had a whole bunch of older customers, long standing older customers, they were all big depositors, nobody borrowing, the business would not be sustainable.
[Rowan Dowland] So over the years, we've driven down the average age of customer.
[Rowan Dowland] So that 34 average age in January 30, the average age, we're probably the only bank in the country where the average age of customer is coming down.
[Rowan Dowland] And it's coming down because people hope, optimism, the role of money in the society.
[Rowan Dowland] So will I get to the point where it's a bank for kids?
[Rowan Dowland] I'll probably won't get to the point where they're all kids.
[Rowan Dowland] But getting younger kids is really, really important.
[Antony McMullen] Question over there, somewhere.
[Antony McMullen] Sonya, I'll get you to choose because there's lots of hands up.
[Antony McMullen] We'll probably take two more questions.
[Audience] Well, I'll try and be short so you can.
[Audience] I borrowed some years back $75,000 from the Credit Union.
[Audience] Actually, it's now part of CUA, Credit Union australia, but it wasn't there.
[Audience] And I moved a house on a small piece of fair land, 52 by 18 meters.
[Audience] I moved an existing house that was going to be demolished.
[Audience] No bank would have given me that money at all.
[Audience] And I got the permit from the local council.
[Audience] I don't know how I got it.
[Audience] And that was turning to three separate well-built units for clients of Kildonan.
[Audience] All right.
[Audience] Yeah.
[Audience] Okay.
[Audience] It was such a small thing.
[Audience] I mean, you can't even say it's a model to copy because it's one.
[Audience] But without the money with the credit union, it took me five years to pay it back.
[Audience] I couldn't have done it.
[Audience] I've been with the credit union for 35 years now.
[Audience] And so have my children.
[Audience] And the living and learning center around for 25 years, no longer, but I did then.
[Audience] Everyone in there working or many of the students were banking with some credit union.
[Audience] just copy that.
[Audience] You don't have to do much effort.
[Audience] And recently, Brother Wilson Lawrence in the monthly lunches had two people from, actually one of them was Trent Hall, to talk about cooperatives.
[Audience] And I would like you to keep them in mind, to invite them perhaps again.
[Audience] I mean, one of them was from the CFMEU.
[Audience] He's a lovely, lovely big guy.
[Audience] You never know, he's really muscle, you could ask him.
[Audience] But he's working on cooperatives.
[Audience] And I think we need to spread that kind of knowledge.
[Antony McMullen] I'll take that as a comment, Ivana, because we've got to, as Tony Jones says, take one from...
[Audience] Yes, sorry.
[Antony McMullen] You still have your question?
[Audience] My question's too big, go ahead.
[Antony McMullen?] Is that last question, or?
[Antony McMullen?] One here and then one there.
[Audience] Thank you, Rowan.
[Audience] Sorry, Basil, but Rowan, you mentioned about credit unions losing their way and banks losing their way.
[Audience] It's wonderful what's happening with Bank australia and credit unions.
[Audience] What's in, in, in process there to ensure that it retains its purpose?
[Audience] My work in other institutions that are value based, that's the issue.
[Audience] How do you ensure the sustainability in the future of that?
[Rowan Dowland] I think there's a couple of ways.
[Rowan Dowland] There's, and let me give you two, two, two answers.
[Rowan Dowland] The first is to continually prove that the business model is successful, that it works.
[Rowan Dowland] Now when I, I remember when I fronted up to the board in 20, in 2002 and said we're going to take a different direction, no longer jobs in geography, no longer teachers and scientists, attitudes and values, just trust me.
[Rowan Dowland] But when you the...
[Rowan Dowland] The board at that time said, what's the evidence?
[Rowan Dowland] And I said, I can't give you any, just trust me, trust the science, trust the evidence that we've done.
[Rowan Dowland] So part of it is good governance and a board that is, the founders that Antony referred to at the beginning, and I've read that paragraph out to our own board, good governance, being bold and being brave, and sitting around that board for all the right reasons, not the wrong reasons, that's part of good governance, a strong sense of purpose and that recognized in your constitution and the like, very, very clear.
[Rowan Dowland] So good governance will hold it true.
[Rowan Dowland] Another element of that is being able to measure and measure the performance of the business, not on profit maximization, but on impact, correct, how the values are derived, delivering wealth defined differently, value defined differently.
[Rowan Dowland] So we will become, you might have heard B Corp, we will become a B Corp in australia.
[Rowan Dowland] A purpose based business, a purpose led business, with a really, really strong sense, there were criteria around measurement in terms of community, in terms of environmental impact, in terms of governance, in terms of workforce.
[Rowan Dowland] So building systems into the business that actually provide the level of discipline that's required to ensure that this is part of the DNA of the organization is critically, critically important.
[Rowan Dowland] But at the end of the day, why is it, why don't you, once I leave, once I leave, how do we keep it going?
[Rowan Dowland] Part of my process, the last five years really has been making sure that we really got good leadership transition in place, transition program and succession in place.
[Rowan Dowland] So I've got my replacement all lined up.
[Rowan Dowland] Fiona Nixon is sitting there already going.
[Rowan Dowland] And that's a process of recognizing that we won't be here forever, clearly.
[Rowan Dowland] But at least make sure that we've got people who share the same principles and values and experiences that are standing right next to us, that can step into those roles when we step away.
[Rowan Dowland] And I joke with the guys and joke with Fiona, that now I'm going to sit in my little village over in Italy and just be amazed at the incredible things that they will have achieved when I've stepped away because they're cleverer than I will ever be.
[Rowan Dowland] They will do things that I will just, I could never even imagine, because we've put that in place.
[Rowan Dowland] So good governance, good processes, systems that measure and report on the things that are important and good succession plan is my, the approach that I've taken to say this can't change.
[Rowan Dowland] Oh, I should say, there's no, there's no, there's not a conversation in the business.
[Rowan Dowland] And we're going into board planning at the moment.
[Rowan Dowland] There's not a single conversation in the business of saying, we should do anything different.
[Audience] No, no, I'm not saying that, but we've seen lots of institutions have lost their way.
[Rowan Dowland] Yeah, and we did, we've been there, we did that in the late 90s.
[Audience] So, then it becomes so critical.
[Audience] What structures and processes do we put in place there?
[Rowan Dowland] It tries to minimize it.
[Rowan Dowland] Yeah, correct.
[Rowan Dowland] Yeah.
[Audience] Yes, I was very impressed by your objective of trying to redefine wealth.
[Audience] I think that's what you said, wasn't it?
[Audience] It seems to me this is the important thing to do.
[Audience] And I wonder if you have any opinions or observations about anything that is taught currently in schools or universities about economics and what they say about the Co-operative and the credit union sector because, you know, it seems to me that it's almost non-existent.
[Audience] It's almost invisible.
[Audience] And that this idea of changing the concepts through education would be a tough thing to do.
[Rowan Dowland] Yeah.
[Rowan Dowland] No, we've said, I was saying to Basil, beginning of this being, something that, and Antony will remember, is something that we did in 2012.
[Rowan Dowland] In 2012 was the International Year of the Co-operative.
[Rowan Dowland] And at the end of the International Year of the Co-operative, and I think Melina is coming on to speak at one of these events, Melina Morrison.
[Rowan Dowland] She and I were working on the International Year of the Co-operative in 2012.
[Rowan Dowland] And we said at the end of this, there's got to be a legacy.
[Rowan Dowland] What do we do after this?
[Rowan Dowland] Don't know.
[Rowan Dowland] It wasn't just a year and then you forget it.
[Rowan Dowland] What do we do?
[Rowan Dowland] So we, in the guideline name, Greg Walton, Melina Morrison and I said, we're going to establish the business Council for Co-operatives and Mutuals.
[Rowan Dowland] We're going to have a business council that represents all Co-operatives and Mutuals, whether they're farming, dairy, whether they're financial, whether they're health insurance, whether they're roadside, Co-operatives and Mutuals in the country.
[Rowan Dowland] And then we defined, well, if you set that up, what are some of the things that we're going to try and achieve?
[Rowan Dowland] I was staggered that in australia, you could complete an MBA and you had no comp set, no awareness whatsoever of other business models, other than pretty much our partnership, the investor owned.
[Rowan Dowland] But Co-operatives and Mutuals were not in the curriculum on any MBA anywhere in the country in 2012.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm advised that they are now.
[Rowan Dowland] Not in every one, but they are.
[Rowan Dowland] You can now complete an MBA on Co-operative and Mutual Enterprise business.
[Rowan Dowland] I remember sitting at a panel here in Melbourne, with one of the very large law firms, very, very large law firms in Melbourne.
[Rowan Dowland] I won't say who it was because I'm embarrassed by saying it.
[Rowan Dowland] But the guy was really nice.
[Rowan Dowland] He said, you're the Co-operative blogger.
[Rowan Dowland] I said, I'm coming to here.
[Rowan Dowland] I'm talking about Co-operative.
[Rowan Dowland] I said, as a courtesy, I'll let you know, I advise all my clients not ever to form a Co-operative or a Mutual.
[Rowan Dowland] seriously?
[Rowan Dowland] Why would you do that?
[Rowan Dowland] He goes, I always advise my clients to become a company under the Corporations Act, because that provides the best, the robust structure for a company.
[Rowan Dowland] And I said to this guy, we're operated, we're a Mutual, but we operate under the Corporations Act.
[Rowan Dowland] We're a company, a company limited by a shareholder vote.
[Rowan Dowland] That's, we are, we operate under the Corps Act, and we're a Mutual.
[Rowan Dowland] And now the Corps Act actually has been changed, through the business Council have changed the Corps Act, so it does recognise Mutual as a status within the Corporations Act, but then it didn't.
[Rowan Dowland] But I said, we're a company.
[Rowan Dowland] So I don't know why you would even say that.
[Rowan Dowland] So when we got up onto the panel, and we're talking about different ownership models, I said, you know what, folks, there's even lawyers in this city that would advise people not to become a Co-operative because they don't even know that we exist under the Corporations Act.
[Rowan Dowland] That level of ignorance is beyond belief.
[Rowan Dowland] But the business council is starting to get that into the curriculum now.
[Rowan Dowland] To get people to understand that cooperatives is a very valid form.
[Rowan Dowland] Mutuals is a very valid form.
[Rowan Dowland] And you can be a mutual that exists in the Corps Act.
[Rowan Dowland] And the Corps Act now, we've got the legislation changed.
[Rowan Dowland] The Corporations Act now says mutual, defines mutual.
[Rowan Dowland] Mutual is never defined.
[Rowan Dowland] The Corporations Act now states you can be a co-op, a company under the Corporations Act and a mutual.
[Rowan Dowland] And this is the definition of mutual.
[Rowan Dowland] It's there.
[Rowan Dowland] It's done.
[Rowan Dowland] So even the lawyers can't use that as an excuse anymore.
[Rowan Dowland] It's there.
[Rowan Dowland] Yeah.
[Antony McMullen] I feel sorry for this gentleman here.
[Antony McMullen] He said he had a very big question.
[Antony McMullen] So I'll put a challenge to you.
[Antony McMullen] If you can find the smallest part, most important part of that question, or I can wrap it up.
[Audience] Okay.
[Audience] How can we expand the mutual cooperative model fast because we have an infrastructure that's been built, that is a pyramid of growth, profit, growth, profit, and returns to shareholders?
[Audience] And how, I don't think that we're going to achieve the definition of the society that we want until we break that model?
[Audience] And what's a couple of good sledgehammers to try?
[Rowan Dowland] There you go.
[Rowan Dowland] So a couple of them.
[Rowan Dowland] My first sledgehammer was the business Council Copies and Mutuals.
[Rowan Dowland] Anthony mentioned a number before.
[Rowan Dowland] About eight out of ten australians are actually members of a Co-operative Mutual member-owned organisation and don't even know it.
[Rowan Dowland] So creating a sense of awareness that you are part of something that actually is around member ownership is really, really critically important.
[Rowan Dowland] And that's part of the role of the business Council Copies and Mutuals, just to get it into the curriculum, work with government.
[Rowan Dowland] So every party now has a Minister for Co-operatives and Mutuals, should have gone, a Minister with a responsibility for Co-operatives or Mutuals never existed before.
[Rowan Dowland] So some of this is part of the process.
[Rowan Dowland] But you know, I think that it's interesting, when we've got record customer acquisition now, they're not joining us because of our ownership model.
[Rowan Dowland] They're not joining us because we're cooperative or mutual, they probably won't even know that.
[Rowan Dowland] They're joining us because of a strong sense of purpose and values alignment.
[Rowan Dowland] And I think that's probably, I can pretty much shut a conversation down instantly by talking about cooperative or mutual ownership structures.
[Rowan Dowland] I can do it, I can get, I can put you into a hypnotic trance.
[Rowan Dowland] But I think I would be able to engage you on a conversation around the role of money in society and how we can create better social, environmental, economic, cultural outcomes if we invest money differently.
[Rowan Dowland] So we as a movement industry, I hope we will one day become a movement again, have to learn how to have the conversation with people using a language that resonates with them and they understand and they want to engage back with us.
[Rowan Dowland] Unfortunately, a lot of us have used really as language that just shut people down.
[Rowan Dowland] We've got to use a different language.
[Basil Varghese] Well, I think we've come to the end of the evening.
[Basil Varghese] So thank you for being here.
[Basil Varghese] And thank you, Rowan, because I think you've created a whole new client group here.
[Basil Varghese] And people are going to be quite committed to it.
[Basil Varghese] And all I wanted to say is that I really appreciate the fact that you've given away how people can actually use their money and to use it with purpose and meaning.
[Basil Varghese] And I think that's what we're...
[Basil Varghese] just one question I'll ask.
[Basil Varghese] You know, there's a great recruitment that you've got.
[Basil Varghese] I'm curious, it was huge numbers.
[Basil Varghese] Did they all...
[Basil Varghese] Did you get a sense to whether they actually were cooperating with others or was it just a very individualistic stance?
[Rowan Dowland] It sounds like a Dorothy...
[Rowan Dowland] Dorothy Dixon sounds like a Dorothy Dixon question.
[Rowan Dowland] I don't know if I should finish on this or not, because we haven't discussed this before.
[Rowan Dowland] Why I'm so confident, hopeful, that we can return to be a movement of people is that for every customer who joins the bank, they tell 11 other people that they've joined the bank, and they do so with great pride, which is amazing.
[Rowan Dowland] There's no other bank in the country where people say, I've actually just shifted my banking to Bank australia, and they tell 11, that's their numbers, 11 other people.
[Rowan Dowland] What was amazing when we went to them and said, okay, well, that sounds really good.
[Rowan Dowland] Maybe we can encourage you to do more of that.
[Rowan Dowland] What could we do?
[Rowan Dowland] What do you need?
[Rowan Dowland] What would you want as an incentive?
[Rowan Dowland] What do we do?
[Rowan Dowland] If could we incentivize you by giving you something?
[Rowan Dowland] And they know what they said.
[Rowan Dowland] If you did that, I'd stop doing it.
[Rowan Dowland] We want nothing from you.
[Rowan Dowland] Nothing.
[Rowan Dowland] We're doing it out because we believe in it.
[Rowan Dowland] So don't give us money.
[Rowan Dowland] Don't give us give outs.
[Rowan Dowland] There's nothing whatsoever.
[Rowan Dowland] Give us nothing other than give us, make us proud to be a customer of the bank.
[Rowan Dowland] And we will continue to tell people to switch their banking.
[Rowan Dowland] That's why I'm so confident that we can rebuild the movement of people that brings about positive change.
[Rowan Dowland] And that's what the Power of Co-operative Bonds is about.
[Basil Varghese] Well, that's great because I think it brings in line just with the sort of community development stuff that Antony and I have been involved with in the past.
[Basil Varghese] There's a thing which I call the Power of Five.
[Basil Varghese] And the Power of Five is this basically, if five people got together, they could actually harness another five each.
[Basil Varghese] So I was just thinking whether your bank could be an initiator to test ideas what people would like to do and to be able to start that movement that we both cherish.
[Rowan Dowland] Absolutely.
[Rowan Dowland] Let's talk.
[Antony McMullen] And I think that's a really good note to end on.
[Antony McMullen] And I would really like to thank both Basil and Rowan for being part of this conversation tonight.
[Antony McMullen] And why I think it's a good note to end on is that the legal minimum number to form a cooperative is, guess how many people?
[Audience] Five.
[Antony McMullen] Exactly.
[Antony McMullen] So you've hit the right number.
[Antony McMullen] So I'd really again like to thank both speakers.
[Antony McMullen] I've learnt a lot.
[Antony McMullen] I think we've gone into the history.
[Antony McMullen] I've learnt a lot about Bank australia.
[Antony McMullen] And I'd also like to recognize Craig who's here from APS Benefits.
[Antony McMullen] It's also a kind of a financial cooperative that I'm a member of personally.
[Antony McMullen] So it's great to have some other stakeholders in the audience.
[Antony McMullen] I'd really like to thank, this has been a new kind of thing that we're trying tonight.
[Antony McMullen] And I'd really like to thank Brian who's recorded tonight.
[Antony McMullen] And I would really like to thank Shannon who's been taking some photographs tonight.
[Antony McMullen] Both of these people are out there doing amazing art, doing kind of amazing things in the IT area.
[Antony McMullen] So have a chat to them afterwards.
[Antony McMullen] Now, we do have a little card here for Rowan.
[Antony McMullen] Now, in some ways it's quite sad.
[Antony McMullen] It's just a card, but it's not a big bottle of wine.
[Antony McMullen] It's not a bunch of flowers.
[Antony McMullen] But it is a card with a heartfelt message.
[Antony McMullen] And it's a card that is hand made, made in New Zealand, with sustainable ink and those kind of things.
[Antony McMullen] And the card features a circle of wise owls.
[Antony McMullen] So that's really what we're trying to achieve tonight, is getting a circle of wise owls.
[Antony McMullen] That includes you as well.
[Antony McMullen] So I'll just give you that, Rowan.
[Antony McMullen] Thank you, Rowan.
[Antony McMullen] And lastly, do we have some feathers for you?
[Antony McMullen] I'd like to thank Sonia, my board member in the Co-operative causeway, who will grab that little tankard of feathers.
[Antony McMullen] Now, what do you think these tankards represent?
[Antony McMullen] Any guesses?
[Antony McMullen] A drink on your way out.
[Antony McMullen] Grab a feather, head down to the bar, and thank you to Rowan and Bank australia for the generosity.
[Antony McMullen] Thank you very much for coming.